<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Shao Kiat's Blog Blog</title>
        <link>https://shaokiat.github.io/shaokiat-blog/blog</link>
        <description>Shao Kiat's Blog Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An Analysis on My Dating App Experience]]></title>
            <link>https://shaokiat.github.io/shaokiat-blog/blog/dating-app-analysis</link>
            <guid>dating-app-analysis</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[These observations and views are purely personal opinions and should be taken with a light-heart 🌝]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="admonition admonition-note alert alert--secondary"><div class="admonition-heading"><h5><span class="admonition-icon"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="14" height="16" viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>disclaimer</h5></div><div class="admonition-content"><p>These observations and views are purely personal opinions and should be taken with a light-heart 🌝</p></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="preamble">Preamble<a class="hash-link" href="#preamble" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>As I begin my work as a data scientist, I thought why not try to analyze some data from my own real-world experiences.
And what dataset could be more interesting than my own dating app experience? So for the month of July 2023, I began tracking
the statistics of my experience with dating apps in Singapore as a 25 years old male and as a free-user.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="part-i-the-game-of-swipes">Part I: The Game of Swipes<a class="hash-link" href="#part-i-the-game-of-swipes" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>First of all, we should all understand the phenomenon in the dating apps scene. I happen to chance upon this fantastic video
that explains the situation with such accuracy, using models and assumptions - a language spoken by data scientists and statisticians.</p><p>Please give the video a watch before continuing and I will be summarizing the learning points from this video and base of my
observations from it as well.</p><div class="dating-app-container"><iframe height="100%" width="90%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/x3lypVnJ0HM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"></iframe><div>Source: Memeable Data on Youtube</div></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-are-men-getting-fewer-matches">Why are men getting fewer matches?<a class="hash-link" href="#why-are-men-getting-fewer-matches" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The median number of matches for men is skewed by the imbalance of several factors:</p><ol><li>Significantly more men than women uses dating apps (Gender imbalance)</li><li>Men give more likes than women (Engagement bias)</li><li>A small share of users get a big share of the likes (Engagement imbalance)</li></ol><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-a-result-of-these">What is a result of these?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-is-a-result-of-these" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Men:</p><ul><li>As men don't get as much likes, they start giving likes more generously to improve their chances of getting matched.</li><li>Studies indicated that dating apps can have a negative impact on self-esteem, with a stronger effect on men.</li></ul><p>Women:</p><ul><li>Women are overwhelmed with choices, making them think more carefully about who they give likes to, and since guys are so
generous with their likes, there is a good chance he is not even genuinely interested.</li><li>Women often have to find strategies to deal with intrusive behavior from men.</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-my-strategy">What My Strategy?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-my-strategy" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>As I believe I do not belong in the top 15%, I naturally applied the strategy as mentioned above. And this means that in
order to acquire more matches, I need to invest additional time in optimizing a good dating profile, and be more generous with my likes.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="part-ii-matches-statistics">Part II: Matches Statistics<a class="hash-link" href="#part-ii-matches-statistics" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Below is a Sankey Chart of the statistics for the month of July 2023.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="sankey-chart-of-dating-app-statistics">Sankey Chart of Dating App Statistics<a class="hash-link" href="#sankey-chart-of-dating-app-statistics" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h4><div style="text-align:center;display:flex;justify-content:space-evenly"><img loading="lazy" src="/shaokiat-blog/img/blog/sankey-dating-app.png" alt="sankey chart" width="800" class="img_ev3q"></div><br><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-could-be-optimised">What could be optimised?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-could-be-optimised" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>From the observation of the chart,</p><ul><li>30% of matches did not end up with any messages at all. And since I have to start the conversations the majority of the
time, perhaps I could be more careful and less generous with my likes.</li><li>27% of matches that did have messages, never replied, possibly indicating that I should look into working on my opening message.</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="limitations">Limitations<a class="hash-link" href="#limitations" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>This chart is limited in information to draw conclusions from, and only offers a big picture view of the statistics.
The chart does not tell me about the quality of the matches from each platform and there could potentially be data imbalance
present in each app, possibly due to different the demographic of the users.</p><p>A more detailed approach could be used to include factors such as user feedback,
satisfaction ratings, success stories, or user demographics. These additional data could then provide some insights into each
the respective dating apps.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a class="hash-link" href="#conclusion" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In conclusion, keeping track of the data from personal experiences is indeed an interesting way to gain insights into my own preferences,
patterns and experiences. This self-reflection can hopefully lead to enhanced decision making, and ultimately an increased
likelihood of finding a potential partner.</p><p>This is definitely a good experiment to get me more proactive and mindful about the data that surrounds me in the digital landscape
as I continue to explore and understand the broader implications of data in my life.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Refreshing View]]></title>
            <link>https://shaokiat.github.io/shaokiat-blog/blog/view</link>
            <guid>view</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is a recount of an experience during my exchange at UC Santa Cruz, that has left me thinking about the stark difference in culture of the US to that of my home country, Singapore.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a recount of an experience during my exchange at UC Santa Cruz, that has left me thinking about the stark difference in culture of the US to that of my home country, Singapore.</p><p>I had embarked on a backpacking trip with the school's recreation club to Big Sur, headed by two amazing student guides. I was joined by my buddy, Vincent, whom I had became good friends with
prior to the trip. We were all thrilled to be part of the expedition and the drive was long but scenic, with breathtaking views of the Pacific Ocean
and towering cliffs that hugged the coastline.</p><p>We began our hike into Big Sur and and eventually to Buckeye Camp where we would settle down for the night.</p><div style="text-align:center;display:flex"><div style="flex:1;padding-right:10px"><img loading="lazy" src="/shaokiat-blog/img/blog/hiking.jpg" alt="hiking" width="300" class="img_ev3q"></div><div style="flex:1;padding-right:10px"><img loading="lazy" src="/shaokiat-blog/img/blog/buckeye.jpg" alt="hiking" width="300" class="img_ev3q"></div></div><br><p>We were extremely lucky that night to experience the most surreal star gazing experience upon the clear, crisp night, along with camping games
that filled the air with laughter and joy. Being able to see the Milky Way with my naked eye was a humbling experience that has left me questioning
my own existence. Every corner of the sky were lit up with countless stars, a scene that would have never existed in Singapore.</p><div style="text-align:center;display:flex;justify-content:space-evenly"><img loading="lazy" src="/shaokiat-blog/img/blog/milkyway.jpg" alt="milky way" width="400" class="img_ev3q"></div><br><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-incident">The Incident<a class="hash-link" href="#the-incident" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>While we were left to our own stations to settle down for the night, my buddy Vincent, decided to roll a joint. Some essential background information is that while
weed is legal in California, it is not legal according to the Federal laws, which still governs State parks and school trips as they receive federal fundings.
As he was about done with the joint, the two student guides found out about it and were furious, stating that this is the first time they had someone smoke on an
expedition. They explained that they were angry as they might lose their jobs, and it was a dangerous fire hazard, especially during the dry Fall season that we are in
right now.</p><p>The two guides then said that they were going to confiscate his 'apparatus' and hand it over to the head of the recreation club. This incident ruined the happy moment
and the mood got really awkward the following morning as we began our hike back.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="face-the-music">Face the Music<a class="hash-link" href="#face-the-music" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>A week later, I met Vincent and what he told me was something that I would never have expected. He said that he met the head of the recreation club to discuss about the smoking
incident, and what was shocking was that instead of giving him a harsh punishment, the head actually apologized on behalf of his student guides for
confiscating his things without permission, and returned his things back to him. In the end, Vincent got let off with a just warning not to do it again.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="stark-differences">Stark Differences<a class="hash-link" href="#stark-differences" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The resolution for this incident left me thinking about the stark difference in cultures, and that how much the Americans value privacy as well as mutual respect. This would
have only been possible if the person of authority respects the people under him to do the right thing and learn from their mistakes.</p><p>From where I came from, it is ingrained in me that incidents like these would have been dealt with the heaviest punishment. We were taught never to question authority,
and people with authority usually gets away with anything they do.</p><p>Now, I am not saying that the resolution is right or wrong, just that it would have never cross my mind that such a resolution is even possible.
This has definitely expanded my horizon as to how people from different cultures deal with conflicts, and there are definitely learning points from this incident.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Questioning of Science]]></title>
            <link>https://shaokiat.github.io/shaokiat-blog/blog/science</link>
            <guid>science</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In this blog post, I want to discuss about a topic that I am deeply passionate about. I have always been a big fan of Science, constantly]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this blog post, I want to discuss about a topic that I am deeply passionate about. I have always been a big fan of Science, constantly
intrigued by how things work, and frequently fascinated by new scientific discoveries. In fact, a person that I really looked up to is none other
than Elon Musk, not because of his riches, but his passion in tackling the hardest problems and playing a major role in advancing the Human race.</p><p>Why I believe the scientific method should be the standard to establish ideas.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-the-scientific-method">What is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_method" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Scientific Method</a>?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-is-the-scientific-method" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><div style="text-align:center"><img loading="lazy" src="/shaokiat-blog/img/scientific_method.png" alt="scientific method" width="300" class="img_ev3q"></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-a-scientific-theory">What is a Scientific Theory?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-is-a-scientific-theory" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>A scientific theory is a well-confirmed framework of ideas that explains (or describes) what we observe.</p><p>Scientific ideas are never absolutely certain. How can we even be absolutely certain about anything? Our brain also has its fair share of flaws.
What we can only do is to establish the best possible theory at that point in time.</p><p>No scientific theory, no matter how strongly supported by
available evidence, is final and unchallengeable; any good
theory is always exposed to the possibility of being modified or
even overthrown by new evidence. That is at the very heart of
the process of science.</p><div style="text-align:right">- American Association of Physics Teachers, 2005</div><p>Source: GEQ1000</p><p>A scientific theory seeks to be disproved and this is what makes it so great. Always adaptable to changes and better ideas.
A process that we should also constantly emulate in our lives.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-then">Why then?<a class="hash-link" href="#why-then" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Perhaps what inspired me to write this blog post is the notion that people readily accepts ideas that cannot be challenged. And that important decisions
and laws are made based on these ideas. How then are we, as a society, supposed to advance?</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Thoughts on (The Two Tiers of Singapore's Tech Companies)]]></title>
            <link>https://shaokiat.github.io/shaokiat-blog/blog/good-company</link>
            <guid>good-company</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Here is an article by Eli James on Singapore's Tech Companies and it has inspired me to think deep about the company]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is an article by Eli James on Singapore's Tech Companies and it has inspired me to think deep about the company
I would want to work at.</p><div class="admonition admonition-tip alert alert--success"><div class="admonition-heading"><h5><span class="admonition-icon"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="16" viewBox="0 0 12 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.5 0C3.48 0 1 2.19 1 5c0 .92.55 2.25 1 3 1.34 2.25 1.78 2.78 2 4v1h5v-1c.22-1.22.66-1.75 2-4 .45-.75 1-2.08 1-3 0-2.81-2.48-5-5.5-5zm3.64 7.48c-.25.44-.47.8-.67 1.11-.86 1.41-1.25 2.06-1.45 3.23-.02.05-.02.11-.02.17H5c0-.06 0-.13-.02-.17-.2-1.17-.59-1.83-1.45-3.23-.2-.31-.42-.67-.67-1.11C2.44 6.78 2 5.65 2 5c0-2.2 2.02-4 4.5-4 1.22 0 2.36.42 3.22 1.19C10.55 2.94 11 3.94 11 5c0 .66-.44 1.78-.86 2.48zM4 14h5c-.23 1.14-1.3 2-2.5 2s-2.27-.86-2.5-2z"></path></svg></span>TIP</h5></div><div class="admonition-content"><p>Read the full article here if you haven't done so!</p><p><strong><a href="http://elijames.org/the-two-tiers-of-singapores-tech-companies/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Two Tiers of Singapore's Tech Companies</a></strong></p></div></div><div class="admonition admonition-note alert alert--secondary"><div class="admonition-heading"><h5><span class="admonition-icon"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="14" height="16" viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>tldr by eli</h5></div><div class="admonition-content"><p>There are two tiers of companies in Singapore - good and bad. People in the bad tier have to fear outsourcing. People in the good tier don’t. Each tier finds it hard to believe the other tier exists. And so the complaints and recommendations for one tier are usually completely different from the other tier, almost as if people are living in two different worlds. This essay describes what these two tiers look like.</p></div></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bad-tier"><em>Bad Tier</em><a class="hash-link" href="#bad-tier" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><blockquote><p>This is where you hear stories about stagnating salaries, where people say that you are at risk of being outsourced, where engineers try to jump to management as quickly as possible, because being an engineer in the bad tier is about as great as being a garment worker in an Industrial Age shirt shop.</p></blockquote><blockquote><p>I’ll define bad tier as "could plausibly be outsourced to a cheaper country"</p></blockquote><blockquote><p>For instance, if software engineers at your company are treated like shit (that is, you can imagine that some day, plausibly, they lay off the team and recruit in India) then it’s likely that the company doesn’t view its programmers as particularly valuable. The business term for this situation is that the company sees the programmers as a "cost centre".
It could be that the work isn’t very important to the business of the company. It could also be that management – rightly or wrongly – doesn’t see much value in maintaining in-house technology.</p></blockquote><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="good-tier"><em>Good Tier</em><a class="hash-link" href="#good-tier" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><blockquote><p>The reason these friends moved out from those companies and found better jobs was because we met up occasionally, and word got out through the computing grapevine that good companies existed out there.</p></blockquote><p>This is something that I definitely agree where we should be open with our friends on job opportunities so that we can all grow together, instead of avoiding discussion
on salary for fear of feeling embarrassed or even boastful. The goal is to better understand our value and figure out a way to get paid what we're worth if that is not already happening. <a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/its-time-to-start-telling-our-friends-how-much-money-we-make" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">See this</a></p><blockquote><p>I’ll talk more about getting into the good tier later. But to me, that isn’t as important as convincing you that it exists.</p></blockquote><blockquote><p>There’s a real difference in optimism when you know good jobs await you around the corner, so long as you figure out how to get into them. It’s much better than thinking all the jobs out there are as bad as the one you’re currently in.</p></blockquote><p>The article places heavy emphasis on the existence of good companies in Singapore, which is good in a sense whereby potential software engineers have knowledge and
optimism to work towards better companies.</p><blockquote><p>being in the good tier doesn’t guarantee high salaries or a good experience...they’re still in a completely different world from the bad tier programmers. They don’t ever have to worry about outsourcing, they know they’re considered high value.</p></blockquote><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="personal-opinions">Personal Opinions<a class="hash-link" href="#personal-opinions" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><blockquote><p>With this good tier/bad tier divide, this is easy to answer: the good tier companies experience the lack of talent, while employees in the bad tier companies complain.</p></blockquote><blockquote><p>When you’re in the bad tier, companies care about what you can do for them. It’s a purely transactional relationship...(some) see these companies and conclude that what you need to do to get hired is "have skill in X", and CS schools don’t teach you "skill in X", so therefore CS curriculums are "outdated" and "bad".
When you get to the good tier...it’s frankly ridiculous to hire people who can “just do X”. You want engineers who can adapt to new technologies, evaluate competing approaches</p></blockquote><p>These are some of the words that struck deep within me - that I must remind myself not to fall into the 'bad tier' of Tech companies where tech is not valued and I will inevitably end up on Reddit complaining. This article serves as a good reference and reminder that I should always be searching and working towards companies that value my skills and contributions I can bring to the team and that I should never settle for less. Of course this is easier said than done and I definitely must put in my utmost effort in preparations for the interviews ahead.</p><p>As of writing this, I have about one and a half years before graduating from NUS and I will make full use of this time to scale and conquer Mount Everest (Good Companies).</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why am I writing this blog?]]></title>
            <link>https://shaokiat.github.io/shaokiat-blog/blog/Welcome</link>
            <guid>Welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This marks the start of my very first blog post and the start of my journey to reach for greater heights.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This marks the start of my very first blog post and the start of my journey to reach for greater heights.
I want to pen down my thoughts through my job search journey as a software engineer and whoever is reading this (yes that's you 😳) will
serve as witness and reminder for me to hold myself accountable 💡.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="about-me">About me<a class="hash-link" href="#about-me" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>As of writing this blog post, I am in my third year of NUS, majoring in Computer Science.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="goals">Goals<a class="hash-link" href="#goals" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><ul><li>Securing a 2022 Summer Internship at a <a href="/shaokiat-blog/blog/good-company">Good</a> company</li><li>Overseas Exchange at University of California</li><li>Securing job at a <a href="/shaokiat-blog/blog/good-company">Good</a> company (SV/SG)</li></ul><p>I had just received an offer to exchange at University of California, a dream come true, yet at the same time feeling uneasy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>